hi welcome back to the long run
uh we're on episode 11. it's called
making it on the tennis team
and we're going to start out with a
story from the lomrium about choksung
and chok means supreme and sung means
a pair of two people okay
and this is an important word in in
secret practice
and i can't tell you about it but anyway
chok song
means the big two and this refers to
two of the most famous disciples of lord
buddha
which is shariputra and mao galiyana
and we know shariputra because he's the
hero
in the heart sutra and he gets to ask a
question
and because of his question we find we
get the heart sutra we get to hear the
whole heart sutra
so the buddha it by the way it is
traditionally taught that these two
disciples of the buddha became
our hearts they reached nirvana but they
reached it on a lower track okay so
they're in this category
both of them are in this category of
people who have reached a very high
personal space where they are
in complete bliss and they kind of
are are not so interested in the
bodhisattva ideal
of trying to meet every living being
and give this promise to them that i
will take care of you
okay they traditionally they're having
too much
bliss in nirvana to to think about that
much so
it happened one day that
lord buddha came to these two
and i don't know if he shook them awake
or i don't know how he did it but he
he he said you know i want to teach you
guys about this higher thing
where you take care of everybody and i i
want you to have this personal
experience
where you meet every living being
i think it would change your life
forever so he encouraged them
and and the reply by these two
arhats was
wow that sounds amazing you know to meet
every single living being that yeah
that would be something special
ever since we reached nirvana we've been
like a bump on a log okay it says here
a uh tree trunk burned by
a an inert tree trunk
burned by fire or something like that
but what it means is
you know we're just totally out of it
you know that
sounds wonderful buddha but you know
don't teach this stuff to us we're
already in this kind of
spaced out place and we're going to be
here for millions of years
you know so chija
you know we're not the people to be
teaching this stuff because we're
already
we're already wrapped up in our personal
nirvana you're kind of wasting your time
with us
okay and so there's this
incident where even this great
arhat who who requested the heart sutra
was staying in this kind of space and
told lord buddha
maybe you shouldn't waste your time on
us because
we're in a bad we're in a good bad place
and and we we can't really do it you
know
mindu papa shari taboo
then uh
defense and he says look shariputra this
arya
he was just faking it okay he
he had not entered a selfish
personal development he was just faking
it you know
and the answer he gave you know don't
waste your time on us
was for the benefit of other people okay
which is uh okay uh nienter wrong
this gong means you know he was faking
it
shari putra was faking it and he was
trying to be a good example
for the other potential
nirvana seekers in their group in their
student group
you know he was trying to say don't make
the same mistake i made
you know don't become immune
to the higher teachings you know don't
make this mistake i made that mistake
you guys don't make it but he was just
faking it
so he's one of those people like in the
heart sutra
that by tradition might even be
considered a buddha
asking another buddha question who's the
other buddha in this case for zero
dollars
right or bodhisattva okay
okay
anyway uh reaching this lower nirvana
is a big obstacle to tsangawa which is
the verb for
buddhahood to become a buddha okay
therefore
so should we skip all the
stages of the lamb which are meant for
people of lower capacity or medium
capacity are you telling me
that we should just skip those lower
steps
and the answer is no matumba means
get good at being sad about the state of
the world
the world get good at it
and then teichenki
you must enter the greater way you must
seek this experience where you meet all
the living beings in the universe
and and personally commit to them to
help them okay
[Music]
yes the purpose
for studying the steps of the path
for people of medium capacity uh
is to get this kind of state of mind
where we are tired of all
all the kinds of life you could live in
this in this samsara
okay in the suffering life okay even a
human life even a wealthy human life
even a wealthy human life with lots of
scriptures around
mixed nuts okay even those we don't want
we want to go beyond those okay
uh language but
it's not the real path wow okay
it's necessary to get to the real path
but it's not the real path it is a part
of the
steps of the path but it's not the path
you want to
get on in the end okay
[Music]
then he says something kind of radical
and i i've
i've seen people misunderstand the
statement uh
uh how do you say it
he says can you show the next picture
okay
i like this next picture okay i don't
know about you
but you know and i haven't gone to a lot
of concerts in my life
but uh in this next picture
uh you see uh okay who are these guys
uh they're playing pretty bad i'll tell
you that
and they're the opening act okay they're
the opening act
and i don't know like you buy a ticket
for a great band
you want to go see them in live in
person
you know it's a two-hour three-hour
concert
and when you get there there's some
other dumb band playing you know
who are not very good and they're called
the opening act in english they're
called the opening eye these are
i don't know somehow they got this job
to play for an hour to waste time so the
real superstar guys
could you know relax in the back and you
have to sit to these guys for an
hour okay what's that got to do with
anything
and then sometimes by the way the
superstar comes on plays two songs goes
away and the bad band comes back
that's what's happening with the long
rim okay
the first part we started uh the first
part we studied
the steps of the path for people of
lesser capacity or medium capacity
people who just want to stay out of the
lower realms
or people who just want to stay out of
any rebirth in general though all of
those
uh people they're not the real practice
okay
they're just the warm-up bear okay
they're just the opening act ben
they're not the what do you call that
you call opening young
there's another name yeah anyway
uh this steps to the path that we spent
years on
that's not the real thing okay that's
not
the real concern that's not the music of
the mom room
that was just to warm you up okay
and and by the way and then he says
something radical
okay you ready for this uh the six
perfections
are also the opening act coming back at
the end
the six perfections are
are also opening act they're not the
main thing that's a
it's an incredible statement okay uh
the steps of the path to to get out of a
lower birth
or to get out of birth in general
they're not the main thing
and the six perfections are not the main
thing
so what's that leave
yeah it's the experience of of meeting
everybody
in the universe and committing to each
one
individually i will help you you know
that
pablo criminal is making a very radical
statement that's the main act that's the
rolling stones
okay that's the thing you've been
waiting to hear
and that's what i want you to focus on
okay very
extraordinary statement i mean if you're
a real
buddhist practitioner you're like wow
that's pretty heavy okay
so great mamas
have written advertisements
for this uh studying
studying this greater way studying the
path of a bodhisattva okay
great llamas in the past have done a
sales job
for this bodhichitta for trying to get
this body to try to have this experience
and one of them is the great fifth
dilemma
uh who lives 1617 to 1682.
no one owen ganto and he wrote a book
called jambel shalom
which we have studied already
it's called the word of manjushri right
he lists uh cool things
that are going to happen if you get this
experience if you can just
get to this experience by the way which
you have to do in meditation
if you can just get to this experience
of meeting
all these beings just get to that okay
10 different things are going to happen
to you okay now
they're not listed so clearly in that
short live room but
but in this long room they're covered in
detail okay
so ever since the days of the fifth day
llama it's been a tradition
at this point to introduce the students
to 10 cool things that are going to
happen to you
if you can reach this peak experience
with every living being okay
let's go through the list briefly
and then papua new guinea is going to go
into great detail
in fact the great detail that the llama
goes into
on these 10 mean that we're not going to
finish the 10 during this retreat we'll
have to finish
them in the next retreat okay but we'll
get part way through the list okay so 10
different amazing things okay number one
if you have this experience
with every living being 10 special
things are going to happen to you
number one
it's the only way
to enter the path of the of the body's
office
okay is to have this experience there is
no other way
okay you have to have this experience
there are many
uh systems like guinea mignon
[Music]
you know the seven step method or
dakshan yamcha
exchanging self and others but they are
methods to get to this experience okay
when you get to this experience only
then can we say you're on the mahayana
then you're on then you're on the higher
path and you don't have to go back
to pick up your lunch or something that
you left in your house
okay uh second
galway and
i love this
from the moment you have that experience
and buddhists talk about you they will
say
tim my son or saji
my son they will start to refer to you
as their son
or your daughter okay and that's such a
sweet thing
when the buddhists start talking to you
about you
as if you were really their son or
daughter and of course they
love all living beings of course they
love all living beings equally
but those living beings who are very
close to joining
the family of enlightened beings they
they have a special
feeling about them and they say my son
they refer to them as my son or my
daughter
and it's very sweet you know if you've
ever had this relationship
i had this relationship with my my heart
teacher
and i uh ken rinpoche and and when he
when people met him he would refer to me
as his son
and it was a very deep deep love deep
thing
so when you when you have this
experience
then the enlightened beings of the
universe start saying oh oh he's he's
one of my sons
she's one of my daughters okay okay
benefit number three
nyan wrong reiki gone
then you join a family you join a select
family
and you are completely different from
other people especially
uh people who are on lower path okay you
are totally
i like to think of it as you are at an
evolutionary higher level okay you are
no longer
even in their league you're in a
different league
okay you're in a different family okay
number four
uh chippishing choke the gira something
cool happens
i don't know this is kind of sexy
but uh if you have had this experience
and people uh
respect you at all for not they get
incredible good karma okay so that's
kind of a
nice reason to have the experience you
see then uh
after that if you're a nice person and
people think you're nice
then they get like 10 billion more seeds
by thinking of you well okay it's kind
of of a strange
benefit or if they give you a cup of tea
then
for them it's like giving
a thousand cups of tea or a million cups
of tea because you're a different person
you're you're a different being
so it's kind of fun to be a person
who if other people uh
get to know you then automatically they
are making great karma okay
all right uh number five sokya chambo de
la tito
[Music]
it's easy for you to collect massive
amounts of good seeds okay
when you have that experience
you get a a number of seeds in your mind
which is
unimaginable and they will carry you to
amazing places
and you know that you if you see that
okay
dig deep near the jawa of course
everybody sapa still has a lot of old
bad seeds
and every bodhisattva even who has seen
emptiness directly or had this
bodhisattva experience but it should
experience
directly they still have a lot of bad
seeds in their mind they still make
mistakes
they have not eliminated the the mental
afflictions
they are not our hearts yet they still
have a lot of problems
okay but they can clean their mind out
relatively faster than than other people
okay
number seven chi samba dupa
any goal spiritual goal you set your
mind to you can achieve it
okay you know i would like to
learn master sanskrit so i could help
more people or something like that or
you know i don't know i'd like to be
able to tell the future
and then i could help people more so
whatever you
dreamer uh you're able to achieve it
okay
uh number eight number one particular
you don't get extraordinary obstacles
okay they they avoid you okay
uh we'll talk by the way each one of
these has a long explanation
which is coming okay i'm just giving you
the ten quickly
salang tangent uh
you can move up through the bodhisattva
levels you can get through the five
paths
very very quickly and reach the end okay
number ten joey deki malu bajue shinstar
yawao you become
a farmer's field in which
all of the wishes of every living being
can grow and be eaten
yummy yummly later okay something like
that
okay all right uh
okay so we're gonna talk about the first
one we still have some time
we're gonna talk about this first we're
gonna talk about the first of the 10
cool things
that happens to you uh if you can get to
this core experience
okay uh domboni and
uh and i'd like to i like to think okay
so uh when i was a kid
my parents got divorced and my mother
had no skills and no money
and she went to school at that time the
only job a woman could get was a
secretary or a school teacher
and she went to school and became a
school teacher
and she had four boys no money
and uh you know our our life was
it wasn't like we were hungry regularly
uh once in a while we were hungry but um
but we had to be careful with money and
uh
i remember one day she said okay boys
we're going to have a family meeting
and we all got there and she said look
we don't have so much money so we're
going to make this
democratic uh we either have money to go
see movies once in a while
or i have money to put you in the tennis
club
you know you can learn to play tennis
intense club
and then then we said mom
okay we would let you know and all four
brothers we went to another room
and we we were talking it over you know
like do you want let's go see movies
yeah i mean who wants to play tennis
and they're like yeah let's vote for the
movies and then
my older brother said no no mom's trying
to trick you
and we said well what do you mean oh she
wants you to vote for the movies because
it's cheaper
and the tennis club is more expensive
and we said but we don't want to learn
tennis just you you do
do means some dumb guy you deuce the
tennis club has a swimming pool
you know you can go swimming anytime you
want you know she didn't tell you that
because it's more expensive vote for the
vote for the tennis club
and then we get to go to the swimming
pool any time we want so you know we all
voted for the tennis club
and then my mom decided we had to learn
tennis to swim in the pool so we
learned tennis she thought
if i think if yoga had existed it would
have been yoga
but she said well this is something that
will keep you fit for the rest of your
life
it doesn't it's not like football you do
football until you're 20 years old and
then you hurt your knees and you stop or
soccer
but uh tennis you can play she played
tennis until a few weeks before she died
so she said this is good this is going
to be good for your whole life so we
learned
but in my youth tennis was considered
very wimpy and only only like
weird kids weird skinny kids
don't show this one yet
that's the punchline uh yeah only weird
you gotta show the last one uh this this
little
little kid little boys with buck teeth
you know they
they this looks like seiji when he's a
kid actually uh
yeah only weird kids who want to play
tennis you know
why are we talking about that uh
later when i got to high school they had
a tennis team
and and if you made it on the team there
were only five guys allowed on the team
six only six guys allowed on the team
and if you made it on the team you got a
special
jacket and if you had this special
jacket it was very easy to get a
girlfriend
so we all wanted this special jacket
letter
leather jacket we all wanted one so i'm
like yeah
i know tennis i can i can get on the
team
so i was trying really hard to get on
the team okay
so this little guy with the tennis
racket is me
uh you know what i want to get on the
team mom
okay here we go tamboni
tell the chum
the question of whether you get on the
team called bodhisattvas
depends on whether you have this
experience or not
got it so if you want to get on the
tennis team meaning
if you want to be on the bodhisattva
team uh
you have to have this experience okay so
that's the first benefit
of having this experience with all
living beings you know if you have it
you're in this special club you get the
special bodies off a jacket
all the body stuff for girls fall in
love with you okay
or the boys okay uh okay
okay it's a long stretch but just put up
with it okay
chad take chain you made me choke it
cause i take chamber too but she's good
even son kappa said i don't
care if the book you're reading is a
bodhisattva's book or not said you're
supposed to
translate the buddhist office so god was
like i don't care
i want to know if you'll join the club
or not you know
take chain parts means are you one of
those
select vip people
who has joined the body software club
who has had that experience
that's that's the only thing i want to
know i don't care what book you're
reading
i don't care what books you're you're
studying i don't care if you're
translating
mahayana books i want to know have you
had that experience or not
okay take chambar and champa young
chandragupta nina
and and whether you've joined that club
only depends on whether you've had that
experience
someday goats
and if your
experience of that experience is just
geshe michael telling you about that
experience
then you are also that kind of
bodhisattva okay
we just talk about you like a voice but
you're not
okay okay you're not on the buddy stop
attract
okay you just can repeat what someone
said about it okay
all right daenerys jensen kappa said
that
so suppose you don't have this
experience and
gigel means the king of all tantras
tartook the ultimate king of all tantras
belsamwa dupa
guhyasa maja which was one of one of
zomkapa's favorite tantras
his real favorite was bad yogini but
that's
you can practice uh the two stages of
tantra
uh from the highest enchanted book there
is
some good
[Music]
that tantra won't even enable you to
enter the first of the fire pass
on the body side of the track okay so
forget the tantrus you know try to have
this experience
do what you can to have this experience
how to have it
study the two methods we have
exchanging stuff in others exchanging
and equalizing
equalizing and exchanging itself and
others and then the seven
uh step method uh taught by
lord achosha we're gonna study it okay
all right
dave partial temperature
if you're studying uh if you're studying
mahayana
and you haven't had this experience then
i would question whether you are
studying mahayana okay
that's kind of heavy uh samdi yana
ban if you have had this experience
mani sachin tembang te chengichu
and all you know how to do is
one time around on your rosary that
becomes
the study of the mahayana teachings okay
young son yahweh and that one
time of reciting that mantra on your
rosary
will be enough to get you enlightened
okay last
thing to show you is this picture
and uh you ready i found it today
uh you know me and veronica found it
better
anyway uh i did make the team
and that was cool okay that guy in the
middle with the hair
is so so it is possible to make this
team
and whether or not you make this team it
just depends on learning those methods
uh equalizing and exchanging yourself
and others
and then just keep trying just keep
doing it
sincerely and you will have that
experience and then there's
and then your life has been valuable
then you've had a good life if you just
have that experience you have a good
life
okay see you then in episode 12.
you